In 1931, Mahandas Gandhi [music]
declared, "If India gains her freedom
through truth and nonviolence, [music] I
feel convinced it will be the largest
contribution of the age to the peace of
the world.
At that moment, Gandhi stood before the
world as the revolutionary and spiritual
leader of the Indian people.
16 years later, India was free.
But independence had not arrived without
[music] horrific violence between
religious communities.
>> [music]
>> This is Delhi. It used to be my family
home. But in 1947, my grandparents, my
mother, my aunt and my uncle left the
city for good. It was the moment that
they stopped being Indian. The moment
that British India became two separate
nations, India and Pakistan.
That division partition was something
that Gandhi had dreaded.
Gandhi's dream had turned into a
nightmare. In the twilight of his life,
India turns its back on Gandhi.
He's sidelined for his failure to master
political negotiations
and his vision for the future nation
state is dismissed.
Even India's most deprived reject him as
their leader.
Yet today, Gandhi is revered as the most
important Indian of all time.
So why is he remembered as [music] the
father of the nation
in September 1931? One, Mahandas Gandhi
aged 61 [music]
arrived in England. His mission to win
India's freedom from the empire.
Gandhi had spent most of his life
fighting for the rights of Indians. In
time, he became the figurehead of the
battle to free India from colonial
domination. His crowning moment came as
he led 70,000 of his countrymen in a
nonviolent protest against the punitive
tax on Indians collecting their own
salt.
The violent British clampdown that
followed brought international outrage
but also [music] international acclaim
for Gandhi.
The man in the loin cloth had shattered
the moral authority of a superpower.
[bell]
[music]
Finally, Britain was listening to Gandhi
and he was invited to London to take
part in the roundt conference on India's
future. At last, he was in the capital
of the empire, poised to bring freedom
one step closer.
It was the opportunity India had been
waiting for. The hopes of a nation
rested [music] on Gandhi's shoulders.
Gandhi's understated manner carried
overwhelming power.
It was how he intended to bring down the
empire. [cheering]
Many who met him couldn't help but be
impressed.
That's a picture of me in 1931, the year
I met him, standing of all places.
>> One of these was a six-year-old boy
called Tony Ben.
>> Well, father was secretary for India. He
invited Gandhi to the second round table
conference, but he asked Mr. Gandhi if
he could bring his children to see him.
And when I went there, I I don't know
what I expected, but I I I I don't think
I had a very clear idea, but the one
thing I noticed was that unlike most
adults, when they talk to a child, they
pat you on the head and talk to your
dad. And he was sitting on the floor and
he said, "Come and sit down. my brother
who's 10 and I sat down and I have no
idea what he said but he made an
enormous impact on me treating us
seriously which children often feel no
one does but he did make a very very
powerful impression on me and I became
interested in him and in nonviolence and
in the campaign for Indian independence.
>> What do you think the appeal of Gandhi
was at the time?
The modesty of his life uh style was one
of the things that made such a big
impression. He didn't um see anything
for himself in it, but he tried to
inspire other people to do what had to
be done and that's why I think he made
such an impact.
Gandhi may have won the hearts and minds
of the British public, but he also had a
political battle to fight
for which he would need shrewd
negotiating skills.
India's independence would not come
without success at the round table
conference at St. James's Palace.
But for this key moment, Gandhi was
remarkably illquipped.
On his way to the first session of the
conference, Gandhi himself revealed just
how unprepared he was. He admitted to a
[music] friend, "I am absolutely blank.
But perhaps God will help me collect my
thoughts at the proper time. All I have
to say is we want independence.
But the politics of India's journey to
independence was about to prove much
more complicated.
Gandhi had come to London as the
representative of India's [music]
Congress party, the organization
spearheading the freedom movement.
For Gandhi, Indian unity was of the
utmost importance and he believed he
spoke [music] for all of his countrymen.
But there were others at the conference
who thought very differently.
To find out what happened, I've come to
the National Archives at Q to meet
historian [music]
Alex vonelman.
Controversially, Alex calls Gandhi one
of the biggest [music] obstacles to
Indian independence.
>> So what are these papers, Alex? These
are some cabinet [music] records of what
went on at the round table conference
which Gandhi attended.
>> Also present were leaders of several
minorities including Sikhs, Muslims and
the untouchables.
They were concerned about [music] how
their rights would be protected in a new
independent India and were asking for
separate representation.
The most significant of these groups was
the Muslim League by Muhammad Ali Jina.
Gandhi by this stage is a really crucial
internationally known figure, isn't he?
But so this conference isn't really
about it's just him negotiating with the
British.
>> Oh no, not at all. I mean, if anything,
it's kind of the opposite. He's sort of
one among so many figures that he almost
becomes obscured. I mean, you had all
sorts of very, very prominent people as
well. So the Muslims are the biggest
minority group, aren't they? What do
they bring to the conference? What is it
that they want at this stage?
>> Well, at this stage, they're worried
about being left out of the majority of
Hindu of the sort of Hindu-led politics
that's running India. So what they
really want is to ensure separate
electorates. They want their own
designated seats and they want to ensure
that those are going to be kept for
Muslims.
>> And what did Gandhi feel about that?
>> He was pretty opposed. Yandi was very
much of the opinion that um there needed
to be a kind of united front and that
then within that you'd ensure kind of
adequate representation, but other
parties didn't really feel that served
their interest.
>> But they're not at this stage talking
about having their own Muslim nation.
>> No, they're not. No. Uh not at all. Um
the whole Pakistan idea actually doesn't
even come up at this point. I think it's
still being talked about by some
students at Cambridge University and
that's the only mention of the word.
Jenna wouldn't embrace that till the
middle 1940s. So there was still scope
at this point for a real agreement on
what a free united India would look
like.
>> Absolutely. I don't think at this point
anyone was even considering really
partition. What you can see happening at
this conference is that the Muslims are
feeling increasingly alienated by the
way that Gandhi is negotiating and in a
sense although you couldn't have seen
that at the time that was sewing the
seeds for what would happen later down
the road
>> for the division of India.
>> Yes.
>> Are you saying that you think Gandhi
bears some responsibility for partition?
undoubtedly.
>> Why would you say that?
>> I think that because he wasn't prepared
to compromise with some of these other
groups, because he made them feel
excluded and because he introduced this
strongly Hindu religious dimension into
politics, I think that forced the
parties further apart.
>> So this opportunity to bring everyone
together to come up with a blueprint for
a free India was lost.
>> Yes, it was completely lost and if
anything, it made matters worse.
The causes of partition are complex
and remain controversial to this day.
But the suggestion that Gandhi could
have played a role in the eventual
division of his country is surprising.
But there's no doubt though that his
refusal to negotiate with the other
delegates did contribute to the failure
of the roundt conference.
[music]
In 1931, India's dream of independence
was no closer to becoming a reality.
Gandhi, the father of the nation, left
Britain empty-handed.
And yet he returned home to a hero's
welcome.
He was still loved as the Indian who had
taken on the British Empire.
But his next move would test the loyalty
of his countrymen. Was he really the man
to lead them to freedom?
Gandhi was back in his homeland and it's
where I'm now heading.
My first stop, Delhi.
>> The Indian people were still pressing
for independence
with negotiations in a stalemate. Gandhi
and the other Congress leaders resumed
their tactic of civil disobedience
against the British Empire
and were immediately thrown in jail.
It was a familiar situation for the
pioneer of nonviolent resistance.
Imprisonment was an effective means of
courting publicity.
In jail, Gandhi's activism continued. He
began a new fast. But what surprised and
confused his allies was that this was
not a fast for the independence of
India. Instead, it was against practices
within his own religion. What Gandhi
wanted was nothing less than a purge of
Hinduism. He called it the greatest
reform of the age.
To the pious Hindu, the mere shadow of a
parrier falling upon him means
defilement. For untouchables are
believed to be undergoing just
punishment for sins committed in an
earlier incarnation.
>> This neighborhood is home to some of the
poorest inhabitants of Delhi.
Today there are people here from
different casts and religions.
But in the 1930s, most of those who
lived in places like this would have
been called the untouchables.
As far as the Hindu cast system was
concerned, they were the lowest of the
low, the scourge of society, the people
who did the jobs that no one else would
touch. Everything from cleaning human
waste to dealing with dead bodies. In
Gandhi's time, there were 50 million of
these outcasts, and it was for them that
he fasted.
Unfashionably, some said recklessly,
Gandhi would devote the next few years
of his life to the untouchables.
He renamed them Harijan, meaning
children of God.
He demanded temples which had for
centuries been closed to the
untouchables now open their doors and he
declared that the only weddings he would
attend would be between Harij Jan and
higher cast Hindus.
The trouble for Gandhi was that someone
else was claiming to represent the
untouchables.
He was an untouchable who had risen to
the status of doctor Pimrao Ramji
Ambedkar.
>> Ambedkar's vision for the untouchables
was focused on their political
representation. He wanted them to have a
separate electorate along the lines of
what the Muslim League had been
demanding. For Gandhi, this was
sacrilege, akin to Hinduism casting off
the untouchables forever. What he wanted
was to bring them into the fold.
[music] And so he began a fast unto
death in protest at Ambedkar's campaign.
>> With the eyes of the world now on a
starving Gandhi, Ambedkar quickly backed
down on his demands. Gandhi got his way.
But victory came at a price. The
campaign was a fight that the
untouchables hadn't asked for.
Today they have rejected Gandhi's term
Harijan.
>> Yeah.
>> Activist Indra Atawali told me why.
So what do you think when you hear the
term Harijan today? So
it I think somebody's abusing me.
>> You see it as an abusive term.
>> Yeah. We don't accept that term minology
for us.
>> Why is that?
>> Because uh this Harian AI is segregating
us from a whole society.
>> So Gandhi is not the liberator of the
untouchables anymore.
>> No no not at all. Gandhi was a strong
supporter of gradation and cast system.
And due and in cast system we were a
billowest one
we were treated as a slaves there.
>> So Gandhi still believed in the cast
system.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Gandhi is not a
liberator of uh untouchables. The credit
goes to Dr. BR Ambedkar to whom we
called Baba Sahab Ambedkar,
>> the father of the untouchable community.
>> Although Gandhi put the untouchables in
the spotlight, he lost their support.
It was a mission that also alienated him
from his closest allies who dismissed it
as a distraction from the fight for
Indian independence.
And yet Gandhi was convinced it was
vital to the struggle for freedom.
>> Gandhi was passionate for untouchable
rights. To help me understand Gandhi's
motives, I've come to meet a historian
with a unique insight. Raj moan Gandhi,
Moandes Gandhi's grandson.
Previously a journalist and political
activist, Raj Moan is now a professor at
the University of Illinois.
I caught up with him during a short
visit to Delhi. However much he wanted
change, he did believe in the cast
system, didn't he? It is undoubtedly
true that for some time, though not for
all time, Gandhi said that in an
idealized form
with division of labor but complete
equality and no hierarchy, the cast
system was a good thing. But Gandhi
added while saying that that such a cast
system does not exist in practice.
>> Did he believe in the cast system or
not?
>> He did not believe in the cast system.
uh he believed you know equality is is
one of the strongest passions in
Gandhi's life. Any notion of hierarchy
that anybody was superior to better than
anybody else was anathema to him.
>> But it was a distraction wasn't it from
the main cause which was India's
freedom.
It was a consolidation of the
independent struggle because unless the
cast Hindus put right or at least tried
to put right their wrongs visa v the
untouchables how could India ask for
independence how could India merit
independence how could India's
independence call be given respect in
the rest of the world it was absolutely
crucial uh to the independence struggle
>> at the heart of Gandhi's mission was his
principle of satyagraha
or seizing hold of the truth.
It had fueled his famous salt marches
and it inspired him. Now Gandhi wasn't
interested in achieving independence at
any price. India must deserve her
freedom.
I can see this would have frustrated his
more [music] pragmatic colleagues in the
Congress party.
And now Gandhi was about to cast himself
even further a drift.
The untouchable cause would remain
important to Gandhi for the rest of his
life. But in 1934, he suddenly announced
that he was retiring from Congress. It
was a puzzling and a risky step. It
meant that he would miss out on the
crucial years when the foundations for
the future India were being laid.
Gandhi's decision was driven by the
realization that a key component [music]
of his Indian dream was about to be
completely ignored.
Back [music] in 1909, Gandhi had
outlined a clear economic blueprint for
a free India.
He wanted a complete rejection of
western notions of urbanization and
modernization.
Instead, his India would be made up of
tiny village republics, wholly
self-sufficient and self-regulated.
But many feared Gandhi's plan would keep
India in the dark ages.
His harshest critic was the man who had
previously been his closest ally,
his friend and disciple, Jawahar al-
Neu.
Neu thought that Gandhi's idealization
of the simple peasant life was an
utterly wrong and harmful doctrine
nothing more than a glamorization of
suffering.
[music]
Ideologically Gandhi and Neu were polls
apart and it was Nehu not Gandhi [music]
who was now the leader of Congress
and who stood to play a decisive role in
shaping the economic future of India.
So what happened to the Gandhian vision?
>> Rudrangu Mukajji is an eminent historian
and editor at the Kolkata Telegraph.
He's written extensively about India's
economic foundation.
>> First and foremost, Gandhi was against
industrialization.
He said industrialization was based on
the production of commodities.
More and more production of commodities
and this led to greed which led to
competition which led to war and
violence. Therefore, Gandhi said that
industrial civilization/
European or Western civilization was
satanic. NU believed that
industrialization was necessary for
progress. Gandhi is not willing to go
along with that. And as the negotiations
begin, Gandhi withdraws from the entire
process. But why does he withdraw rather
than try to convince people?
>> He tried and he described himself as a
back number. He said nobody listens to
me anymore. He just couldn't persuade
them to think along his lines. So he
just withdrew from the process.
>> So how much of an impact has Gandhi's
economic vision had on today's India?
>> None.
India independent India has turned its
back on Gandhi
and it began in the NU era and it's more
true even today post liberalization.
Gandhi didn't [music] believe in the
market. Gandhi Gandhi didn't believe in
a planned economy.
I don't think there is anything in the
economic project that India has come to
represent or India [music] stands for
that is Gandhian
[music] back in the 1920s. Gandhi's
inspirational nonviolent marches had
earned him the title father of the
nation.
But now the seeds of the future India
were instead being sown by Neu.
Estranged from the center of power,
Gandhi retreated to his ashram and spent
the rest of the 1930s living out his
vision of self-sufficiency.
The India that he had once dreamed of
was slowly slipping away.
It was as if Gandhi had served his
purpose. He had spearheaded the struggle
for independence. But his campaign for
the untouchables and his economic ideas
just weren't wanted. By the end of the
1930s, you might have thought that he
was a spent force. But in truth, Gandhi
was far from finished.
In 1939,
India went to war.
As a colony of the British Empire, it
had no choice but to enter World War II.
Its soldiers were expected to risk their
lives fighting for someone else's
freedom and democracy.
But ironically, it was World War II that
would finally bring [music] India her
freedom.
By the end of the war, the political
landscape had dramatically changed.
Britain was bankrupt and India was now a
burden. A burden that it was keen to be
rid of. It seemed that Gandhi's dream of
independence was about to become a
reality, but not in the way that he
wanted. Instead, India was now on course
for partition.
Its leaders were now seriously
considering dividing the country
with a separate state for Muslims,
Pakistan.
It was what Gandhi had dreaded. In his
free India, all its people would live
together as one nation.
And now another of his fears was about
to come true.
Kolkata,
forever evoked by its colonial name,
Kolkata.
With 15 million people and a stifling
tropical climate,
it can be an oppressive city.
In postwar India, it was a pressure
cooker.
The plan to break up the country along
religious lines created fear and
suspicion amongst communities already
stretched to breaking point by mass
unemployment and famine.
The sweltering summer of 1946 would see
Kolkata reach fever pitch.
On August the 16th, after another round
of failed political negotiations, the
Muslim League organized a day of protest
here in the city.
It quickly deteriorated into communal
violence between Muslims and Hindus.
Thousands lost their lives.
The massacres soon spread to the
surrounding countryside.
Gandhi was horrified at how the people
of India were turning on each other.
He came here to rural Bengal, the scene
of some of the worst violence.
He traveled around on foot talking to
people, trying to diffuse the tension.
>> [music]
>> But while he was here, he did something
else. Something that would disturb even
his closest aids, but something that he
was convinced would help end the
violence.
He summoned his 19-year-old great niece,
Manu, to him and arranged to sleep naked
next to her. It was to be a test of his
chastity.
Gandhi believed that his well-being was
inextricably linked to India's and that
outbreaks of violence were a direct
result of his own lack of
self-disipline,
his failure to control his body.
He was now 77 years old.
I've come to meet with Lakshmi Singh
Tikari who for 12 years has been
following the ancient Hindu practice of
brahmacharia or celibacy.
Gandhi's actions at this point will seem
pretty incomprehensible to many people.
Can you help me try to understand what
he's thinking at this point? Gandhi took
on a brahmachara which means reframing
yourself and not just physically but
basically controlling the mind.
>> The discipline then tells you that you
must be able to hold yourself back and
go within
>> and exercising self-control has an
impact on external events.
>> That's absolutely right. by practicing a
life of restraint, you know, that gave
him so much strength that when he said
something or when he meant something, it
would filter down to the people who were
all around him. But I think the
difficulty people will have is not on
the idea of the exercise in
self-discipline and deciding to lead a
celibate life. It's the idea of testing
it in bed with young people.
Well, it's it's quite simple. If you
need to test yourself, you need to test
yourself with the best. You don't test
yourself with with somebody who you've
been for your entire life cuz there's no
testing. You know yourself and you know
the individual. It's when you have a
challenge from outside, a new challenge
which you've never faced and that's when
the test starts.
But these might be vulnerable young
people who
may be unduly influenced. It doesn't
really seem fair.
I think we react to certain things
immediately. You see an old man, you see
a young girl and your mind immediately
runs to the fact that you know, oh, he's
a dirty old man. You know what's he up
to?
Whereas both of them gain
the elder person gains energy and
[music] inspiration and also is willing
is is in a position to be able to give
so much [music] to the younger
generation.
However pure his intentions, Gandhi's
actions distressed both his friends and
the wider [music] public.
They despaed at his esoteric efforts to
stop the [music] violence. A great man
seemingly out of touch with reality.
But before too long, India would once
again turn to its Mahatma.
As Gandhi traveled around the
countryside, desperately trying to stop
his people from destroying each other,
India was on the brink of a historic
moment.
>> The gate of freedom is open in India.
[music]
Lord Louis Mountbatton, last [music]
viceroy of India, arrives to take part
in the official end of British rule.
On August the 15th, 1947, India's
leaders finally gained the power to
govern their own land.
Jawahar Lu became the first prime
minister.
India was free at last.
[cheering]
It was Gandhi who had first galvanized
the nation. Gandhi who had brought
India's cause to international
attention.
And so at the moment of independence,
Gandhi was held up as the man
responsible.
But this is not how he saw himself.
He's completely disenchanted. He's a
broken man. He doesn't think that this
is the independence for which he
struggled. This is not the independence
that for which he mobilized the people
because two of his dreams
nonviolence and the unity of India,
Hindu Muslim unity, they are both
completely broken apart in front of his
eyes at the very moment which could have
been
the moment of his triumph. And I think
among the many ironies of that period,
the supreme irony is the fact that the
father of the nation is not present at
the birth of the Indian nation. Gandhi
chooses and I think I'd emphasize that
word chooses to stay away from Delhi at
the very moment of India's independence.
>> But it is in Gandhi's darkest hour that
India glimpses his true worth.
He'd chosen to spend the moment of
independence here in Kolkata,
a city once again in turmoil.
Muslims, Sikhs and Hindus, all fearing
for their homes and their lives.
Gandhi refused to stand by and watch his
people destroy each other.
He teamed up with the local Muslim
leader Hassan Shahid Surawwardi.
Together they set up camp in this house
abandoned by Muslims fearful of Hindu
attack.
Gandhi had put himself in the front line
of the action.
Immediately after they've entered this
house, there's a very turbulent
mob of young men who come into this
building and demand that Gandhi leaves
immediately.
Gandhi actually says that, you know, you
can do anything you want, but I'm not
leaving. You can kill me, but I'm here
to do what I believe in, and I'm not
going to leave uh till there is a single
Muslim in this area who is still
frightened. And this statement somehow
strikes a chord in the hearts of the
people who had come to accuse him and
they suddenly fall silent.
That hostile crowd suddenly became a
cooperative crowd and they said that
they would let Gandhi stay here and they
would actually cooperate with what
Gandhi was trying to do and see to it
that peace and normaly returned to this
area.
It was the miracle of the Maine. People
of that time saw it as such and they
actually believe that it was only
Gandhi's presence that had made this
magic possible.
I think it's one of the greatest phases
of his life if not the greatest. I would
in fact stick my neck out and say it is
probably the greatest phase of his life.
India's independence movement had been
defined by nonviolence. But the actual
long- aaited event was quite the
opposite. It's thought that 2 million
people died in indiscriminate communal
slaughter.
So what Gandhi achieved in Kolkata was
extraordinary. By coming here he had
brought peace.
The man they called Bapu, father had won
the hearts of the people of Kolkata.
But all over India, communities were
still turning on each other.
And so he left Kolkata to try and bring
peace elsewhere.
The challenge he faced was overwhelming.
Hindus and Sikhs were heading for India
and Muslims were leaving for their new
homeland of Pakistan.
Partition would change the course of
millions of lives forever,
including those of my own family.
In 1947 in the dying days of the Raj, my
grandfather was a young Indian army
officer here in Delhi serving as an aid
to the army chief Field Marshall Orin.
My grandparents, my aunt, uncle, and my
mother all lived in this street. I've
often tried to picture what their life
here was like, but the house is now the
home of an Indian cabinet minister, and
I haven't been allowed inside.
It's disappointing not to see where my
family once lived.
But their time in Delhi is recorded in
my grandfather's partition diary.
It was later published as a book.
Reading the entries, it's clear just how
unsettling those days were. Slowly
[music]
looking through the diary, you get a
sense of how the reality of the violence
starts to unfold. So by September 1947,
he becomes really anxious about his
family who are still in northern India
and he wants to get them to safety in
Pakistan. And then by October he says
the situation in East Punjab is
shocking. There is wholesale slaughter
of the refugees both on the line of
march and in [music] the trains. The
refugee camps in Delhi are in a
deplorable state and Kolera is fast
spreading among the occupants. So by
this stage it's really clear just quite
how horrifying the violence has been
that summer.
My family are very fortunate and are
flown to their new home of Pakistan in
the field marshals plane.
They avoid those notorious trains across
the border.
By now, religious persecution was
widespread.
Muslims, Sikhs, and Hindus, all equally
perpetrators and victims.
Pakistan was simply too far for many
Muslims to travel.
Tens of thousands stayed here in Delhi.
Those left behind faced the terror of
being forced out of their homes to an
uncertain fate.
It was these Muslims that Gandhi now
looked to help.
It was now too dangerous for him to stay
at his usual resting place in the slums
of Delhi's sweepers colony. Instead, he
stayed [music] at the home of a
benefactor, Bir House.
Here
Gandhi began his final fast for the
rights of the Muslims remaining in
Delhi. He demanded that Hindus end their
boycott of Muslim shops, that Muslims be
allowed to hold their own religious
festivities, that mosques seized from
them be returned, and that they should
be able to live safely in their own
homes. On the sixth day of his fast, a
100red representatives of Delhi's
different communities came here and
signed a declaration protecting Muslim
rights. Gandhi's demands were met. The
fast was over.
My grandparents were skeptical about
Gandhi's efforts towards Muslims, but I
don't think this was entirely fair.
I believe Gandhi was genuine about Hindu
Muslim unity and I do feel deeply moved
at the countless lives he saved.
But in helping Muslims, Gandhi was
putting his own life at risk.
Some Hindu extremists felt he was a
traitor to their faith. Gandhi's
remarkable life would soon be over.
During his last days, he held public
prayer meetings here at Berla House.
His grandson Raj Muan was 11 [music] at
the time.
There were occasions when I was also
there. I walked with him sometimes as
one of his walking sticks. Um, and then
often there was banter and he was a
great tease as far as his grandchildren
were concerned. He teased us. no end.
And uh and his way of greeting us was to
give a great thump on the back. Uh and
uh although he was an old man and
sometimes fasting man, his thumb was
quite memorable.
He looked forward to these times when
his family members were with him. These
were brief times, but he obviously
enjoyed them.
And of course at this time we used to
have these prayer meetings on the
grounds here. The prayer meeting would
start with a Buddhist chant and the next
item was the opening chapter of the
Quran.
>> And how did people feel about that
Hindus when they heard that?
>> Most of them were perfectly okay with
with that. But occasionally and I saw
this myself some of them would stand up
and say we don't want that. we won't
allow this. Please stop this.
>> So, were there real threats to his life
at this stage?
>> Yes, he was uh expecting uh he was ready
to be attacked, to be killed. There had
been attempts on his life. I was very
young, but I was aware of this. And of
course, I did sometimes ask myself that
if there was an attack, actual attack on
him and I was near him, how would I
protect him?
Friends and comrades,
the light has gone out of our lives and
there is darkness everywhere
and I do not quite know what to [music]
tell you and how to say it. Our beloved
leader Baku as we called him the father
of the nation is no more.
These footprints mark Gandhi's last
steps. On the 30th of January 1948, he
was walking through this garden on his
way to the daily prayer meeting when a
man approached him and shot him [music]
three times.
He died shortly afterwards.
By the time we arrived here, there was
an immense crowd. Immense crowd. It was
almost impossible for us to make our way
through. Uh somehow we explained who we
were. So we were able to go into his
room and there he was. Um body was laid
out on a white sheet on this thin carpet
on the room and surrounded by flowers
and there were prayers taking place. My
father was there, Mount Batton was
there, Nu was there.
There was no anger in the room at all.
There was sadness
but there was also a sense of peace.
And in my
kind of childish
naive expectation, I thought that this
remarkable man, my grandfather would,
you know, stand up and start to walk
again.
His
assassin [music] was Natam Gods, a Hindu
extremist who saw Gandhi as a traitor
[music] to his country.
Gods believed Gandhi had allowed India
to [music] be partitioned
and his campaign for Muslim rights had
been the final straw. [music]
Gandhi was 79 years old. He had never
wavered [music] from the conviction that
he was the key to saving India.
Some say that proved to be his weakness
but in death it would be his strength.
[music]
Gandhi wanted to be killed like that.
And in fact the day before the
assassination he says what I want is a
death at the hands of an assassin.
>> Historian Trip Surude has spent a
lifetime fascinated with Gandhi's
legacy.
>> And I think Gandhi wanted an action
which would tell the world that it was a
truthful life and I think martyrdom in
that sense gives you the final proof of
your truth.
>> Did he give up then? No, he did not give
up. I think what is that one final act
which stops the violence. It is Gandhi's
assassination.
The nation is stunned into silence. All
violence in this part of the country and
even Pakistan
stops. I think every man and woman felt
that they had also contributed to that
assassination to that act by by their
silence or or or by being violent or by
having contested Gandhi's vision of what
this country could be. It was not one
assassin that killed Gandhi.
>> So you see it ultimately as something
positive
>> very very very enabling in modern India.
I don't think there's been one act which
has made us more noble and more moral uh
than the assassination of Gandhi.
I began this journey in Gandhi's
footsteps ambivalent skeptical about
him. I end it with very different
feelings.
He was not perfect. He was not a saint
and we do him a disservice by putting
him on a pedestal that prevents us
really learning from his life. He had
his eccentricities. He could be
frustrating, infuriating even to those
closest to him.
But he was a man of tremendous personal
courage, a revolutionary without the
violence,
a man who could transform a nation. He
stood for the power of an individual to
bring about change.
Of course, we'll go on debating [music]
Gandhi's ideals.
Is his vision of religious unity
achievable?
Never mind desirable.
One thing is certain to the last he
believed in seizing hold of the truth.
[music]
A recording of Gandhi speaking in London
in 1931 reminds us of what it was that
fired [music] and nourished the father
of a nation and the conscience of a
century.
I do dimly perceive that whilst
everything around me is ever changing,
ever dying, there is underlying all that
change a living power that is
changeless,
that holds all together,
that creates, dissolves and recreates.
[music]
That informing power of spirit is God.
In the midst of death, life persists.
In the midst of untruth, truth persists.
In the midst of darkness, light
persists.
Heat.